King Lear Archive
Rare Book and Special Collections Division Library of Congress
King Lear Archive,1984-1986
Z232.J36 K56 1984
Van Vliet, Claire.
ca. 965 items
Rare Book and Special Collections Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Preparatory materials for an edition of Shakespeare's King Lear published by Theodore Press with illustrations printed at the Janus Press.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Alpert, Michael.; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616. King Lear. 1986.; Van Vliet, Claire, collector.
Organizations
Janus Press.; Janus Press.; King Lear Archive (Library of Congress) DLC; Theodore Press.
Subjects
Book design--United States--History--20th century--Sources.; Lear, King (Legendary character)--Drama.
Form/Genre
Artists' proofs.; Book designers' mock-ups (Publishing); Corrected proofs (Printing); Wood blocks.; Woodcuts.
Occupations
Book designers--Vermont.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Purchase from Joshua Heller Rare Books, 31 Jan. 1991.
Access and Restrictions
The records of the King Lear Archive are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Rare Book and Special Collections Division reading room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of woodcuts, drawings, correspondence, proofs, book designers' mockups, and woodblocks for an edition of Shakespeare's The Tragedie of King Lear published by Theodore Press in 1986 with illustrations by Claire Van Vliet. The publication is based on the 1623 first folio text of the play, and was produced in a limited edition of 160 copies, each signed by Claire Van Vliet. The woodcuts include several proofs of each illustration, most of which are images of characters in the drama. The collection also includes preliminary pencil drawings for each of the woodcuts, as well as a complete set of the original wood blocks. Correspondence relating to all aspects of the project during 1985 and 1986 is chiefly by Claire Van Vliet, founder of Janus Press, and Michael Alpert, owner of Theodore Press. The collection was assembled and arranged by Claire Van Vliet.
Organization of the Papers
Organized in 13 containers: 1-5. Woodcuts; 6. Drawings; 7. Letters; 8. Trial proofs; 9. Dummies; 10. Corrected proofs; 11. Paste-up; 12. Mock-up;13. Wood blocks.
http://lccn.loc.gov/92162930
Container List
- Woodcuts
  - Gonerill, (6 items) (Container 1, Folder 1)
  - Regan, (11 items) (Folder 2)
  - Cordelia, (19 items) (Folder 3)
  - Lear, (35 items) (Folder 4)
  - Gonerill & Regan, (14 items) (Folder 5)
  - Edmund, (12 items) (Folder 6)
  - Fool, (12 items) (Folder 7)
  - Lear Enraged, (8 items) (Folder 8)
  - Gloucester angry, (6 items) (Container 2, Folder 9)
  - Gloucester grief, (21 items) (Folder 10)
  - Kent in stocks, (2 items) (Folder 11)
  - Lear commanding Gloucester, (22 items) (Folder 12)
  - Lear "How is that?", (6 items) (Folder 13)
  - Cruel Gonerill, (15 items) (Folder 14)
  - Cruel Regan, (19 items) (Folder 15)
  - Lear in the Storm, (14 items) (Folder 16)
  - Poor Tom, (11 items) (Container 3, Folder 17)
  - The Storm, (4 items) (Folder 18)
  - Gloucester seized, (5 items) (Folder 19)
  - Gloucester blinded, (3 items) (Folder 20)
  - Edgar finds blind Gloucester, (25 items) (Folder 21)
  - Curran and Gonerill, (9 items) (Folder 22)
  - Cordelia searching for Lear, (29 items) (Folder 23)
  - Curran and Regan, (7 items) (Folder 24)
  - Dover, (18 items) (Container 4, Folder 25)
  - Mad Lear, (7 items) (Folder 26)
  - Lear recognizes Gloucester, (13 items) (Folder 27)
  - Cordelia kisses sleeping Lear, (23 items) (Folder 28)
  - Lear awakens, (19 items) (Folder 29)
  - Edmund, (6 items) (Folder 30)
  - Lear takes Cordelia to prison, (17 items) (Container 5, Folder 31)
  - The Sisters, (2 items) (Folder 32)
  - Gonerill and Regan dead, (5 items) (Folder 33)
  - Edmund repents, (3 items) (Folder 34)
  - Cordelia and Lear, (15 items) (Folder 35)
  - Lear dying, (9 items) (Folder 36)
- Drawings (Container 6)
  One bound volume with preliminary graphite drawings for 39 woodcuts (41 drawings, including 3 double-page spreads)
- Correspondence, 1984-1986, n.d. (Container 7)
  - Alpert, Michael, 1984-1986, (53 items) (Folder 1)
  - Burman, Lorene, 1985-1986, (5 items) (Folder 2)
  - Conant, Judi, 1985, (3 items) (Folder 3)
  - MacGregor, Katie, 1985, (17 items) (Folder 4)
  - Van Vliet, Claire, 1984-1986, (53 items) (Folder 5)
  - W. Thomas Taylor (Firm), 1985-1986, (9 items) (Folder 6)
  - "A-Z" miscellany, 1985, n.d., (7 items) (Folder 7)
- Trial Proofs, (95 items) (Container 8)
  - Xeroxed copy of Nonesuch edition of King Lear, with annotations in pencil and ink, (51 items)
  - Xeroxed copy of Norton facsimile of First Folio edition of King Lear with annotations in pencil, (27 items)
  - Trial proofs, (17 items)
- Dummies, (32 items) (Container 9)
  - 2 sheets of paper folded into 72 rectangles with text and illustrations indicated, (1 item)
  - Sample sheet of "Joanna Western Buckram", (1 item)
  - Two reduced xeroxed paste-ups with preliminary pencil sketches for illustrations, in paper chemises, one with 12 numbered signatures; the second with 12 numbered and 3 unnumbered signatures, (27 items)
  - Miniature flat mock-up of binding (birch board and pigskin) (1), (1 item)
  - Two full-size samples of birch binding boards, one decorated and one plain (2), (1 item)
- Corrected proofs, (86 items) (Container 10)
  - Proofs, (68 items)
  - Notes from Lorene Burman (proofreader) to Michael Alpert with pages, (6 items)
  - Letters written by Lorene Burman to Michael Alpert, (12 items)
- Paste-up (Container 11)
  Bound volume with 39 woodcuts pasted in
- Mock-up (Container 12)
  Miniature mock-up of bound volume in case
- Wood blocks, (42 items) (Container 13)
Bibliography
Fine, Ruth.The Janus Press, 1981-1990: Catalogue Raisonné. Burlington, Vt.: University of Vermont Libraries, 1992.
Shakespeare, William.The Tragedie of King Lear. Bangor: Theodore Press, 1986.
Taylor, W. Thomas. "Claire Van Vliet's Janus Press," American Craft 47 (February/March 1987): 52-59.